<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>TLSeminar</title>
    <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on TLSeminar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://tlseminar.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Padding Oracle Attacks</title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/padding-oracle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/padding-oracle/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;script src=&#39;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/https://tlseminar.github.io/first-few-milliseconds/&#34;&gt;Last week&lt;/a&gt;, we
examined how the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol provides a
private channel between two devices by following the handshake and
record layers protocols. The handshake layer establishes a symmetric
key that both the client and the server could use in the record layer
to encrypt and decrypt messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss a real-world TLS attack, the Padding Oracle
Attack, that takes advantage of our need for each message to be a
particular set length. If the original message is not long enough,
then we have to add padding for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/analysisssl3.pdf&#34;&gt;CBC Mode
Encryption&lt;/a&gt; to
work. Because the padding is present, an attacker can chip away
information on the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/beast.pdf&#34;&gt;ciphertext&lt;/a&gt;, one byte at
a time, through analyzing the receiver’s error messages for the
sender, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isg.rhul.ac.uk/tls/TLStiming.pdf&#34;&gt;response time&lt;/a&gt;,
and general behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll start out by learning about how &lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/analysisssl3.pdf&#34;&gt;CBC Mode
Encryption&lt;/a&gt; works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;padding-and-cbc-mode&#34;&gt;Padding and CBC Mode&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/analysisssl3.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analysis of the SSL 3.0 Protocol&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by David Wagner and Bruce Schneider (1997)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When AES-128 encryption is performed in cipher block chaining mode
(CBC mode), the plaintext message is first split up into 16-byte
(128-bit) blocks. It is often the case, however, that the length of
the message is not perfectly divisible by 16. To account for varying
message sizes, extra bytes, called padding, are concatenated after the
end of the message to fill up the remaining quota for the final block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bytes are not chosen at random, however, and different cipher
modes prescribe different padding methods. In order to clearly mark
for the recipient where the message ends and the padding begins, the
padding follows a strict formatting pattern. With PKCS #5 padding as
used in TLS, if there are &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; bytes of padding, then each padding byte
contains the value &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;. For instance, if the last block contains 15
message bytes, the 1-byte padding contains &lt;code&gt;0x01&lt;/code&gt;; if the last block
contains 14 message bytes, the 2-byte padding contains &lt;code&gt;0x0202&lt;/code&gt;;
3-byte padding contains &lt;code&gt;0x030303&lt;/code&gt;; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/paddingoracle/padding.png&#34; alt=&#34;Padding&#34;&gt;&lt;Br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Source: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.gdssecurity.com/labs/2010/9/14/automated-padding-oracle-attacks-with-padbuster.html&#34;&gt;Gotham Digital Science&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CBC mode, the bytes of each plaintext block n are first XOR’ed with
the encrypted bytes of the block before it, and their result is then
encrypted. Block 1 is the obvious exception, which is XOR’ed with a
fixed, random, or secret initialization vector (IV). Thus, for any
block &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; 1, where E&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; is the encryption function,
&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; is the encrypted block &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; is the plaintext
block &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;-1&lt;/sub&gt; is the encrypted block &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;-1,
&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = E&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;⊕ &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;-1&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/paddingoracle/cbc.png&#34; alt=&#34;cbc-mode&#34; /&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Source: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.rit.edu/~ark/fall2012/482/module05/CbcEncrypt.png&#34;&gt;Alan Kaminsky&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the predictability of the padding format can turn out to be an extremely exploitable weakness for an active attacker. Under SSL/TLS protocol, when servers receive an encrypted message, their first step upon decryption is to check the validity of the padding; that is, determine if the number(s) at the end of the last block represent the number of padding bytes. As soon as this step is completed, the server will return to the sender either an error code or an acknowledgment that the padding is valid. In this way, the server can act as an oracle to an active attacker, providing them with confirmations/rejections to inform their guesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;padding-oracle-attack&#34;&gt;Padding Oracle Attack&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;security-flaws-induced-by-cbc-padding-applications-to-ssl-ispec-wtls-http-www-iacr-org-cryptodb-archive-2002-eurocrypt-2850-2850-pdf-by-serge-vaudenay&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iacr.org/cryptodb/archive/2002/EUROCRYPT/2850/2850.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Security Flaws Induced by CBC Padding Applications to SSL, ISPEC, WTLS&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Serge Vaudenay&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin, the attacker creates a Last Word Oracle. This first assumes a 1-byte padding, so the format that the oracle would return as valid is 0x01 XOR’ed with some particular value in the corresponding last position in the n-1th block. Since the last byte, or word, can have 256 distinct values, the attacker can simply manipulate the n-1th block, easily testing all values, until either the possibilities are exhausted or the padding is returned as valid. If the possibilities are exhausted, then the attacker instead tries 0x02, then 0x03, and on until the padding returned is valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/paddingoracle/last-word.png&#34; alt=&#34;LastWordOracle&#34; /&gt; &lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rsaconference.com/writable/presentations/file_upload/asec-403.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.rsaconference.com/writable/presentations/file_upload/asec-403.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the attacker has learned the padding, a Block Decryption Oracle is constructed, using the values of the encrypted n-1th block to, byte by byte, guess the preceding byte, using the oracle’s pass/fail responses to confirm correct guesses. This method is then extended to decrypt all other blocks, as it is called on pairs containing a random block and a ciphertext block. (Again, the logical exception is the first block, assuming an independent initialization vector.) This is a terrifyingly efficient attack; to implement it, the attacker only needs (b * W * N)/2 trials, where b is the number of bytes per block, W is the number of possible bytes, and N is the number of blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the CBC Padding now added to the original ciphered message, attackers can alter this new message with blockwise operations in order to draw information out of the originally unreadable ciphertext. This information could potentially end up being authentication tokens, such as cookies, granting attackers personally identifiable information or the potential to hijack previous sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;beast-plaintext-attacks-against-ssl&#34;&gt;BEAST: Plaintext Attacks Against SSL&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;here-come-the-oplus-ninjas-https-tlseminar-github-io-docs-beast-pdf-by-thai-duong-and-juliano-rizzo-2011&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/beast.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here Come The \(\oplus\) Ninjas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Thai Duong and Juliano Rizzo (2011)&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CBC block encryption, each plaintext block is XORed with the ciphertext of the previous block before being encrypted. An attempted guess at a plaintext block can be evaluated by encrypting the ciphertext prior to the block in question XORed with the ciphertext prior to the current block XORed with the guess; if the new ciphertext matches that of the block in question, then the guess is correct. E&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt;(P&lt;sub&gt;j⊕&lt;/sub&gt;C&lt;sub&gt;j-1&lt;/sub&gt;) = C&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;mdash; C&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;==C&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; iff P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; == P&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt;⊕C&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt;⊕C&lt;sub&gt;j-1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;mdash; guess G can be evaluated as equal to or unequal to plaintext P&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; by setting P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;=G⊕C&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt;⊕C&lt;sub&gt;j-1&lt;/sub&gt; and checking whether or not C&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt;==C&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;. An attacker would need to be able to view the encrypted messages and query the underlying CBC encryption system to be able to mount an attack based on this exploit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cryptographic systems are limited in their size and ability to store large plaintext messages, for this reason, most cryptographic systems encrypt messages block by block as they are sent in. In the case that an attacker can append padding to a message before it is encrypted, an attacker can mount a blockwise chosen-boundary attack, in which the first byte of an unknown message is isolated by padding, enabling the attacker to guess at single bytes of a message rather than block-sized chunks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural extension of this is to repeat the process such that once a byte of message has been guessed by the attacker, the padding is changed such that a single unknown byte of message is encrypted with padding and bytes known to the attacker, allowing them to continue guessing at single bytes of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Duong and Rizzo go on to describe the process by which this attack could be mounted on HTTPS to obtain a user’s HTTP cookie. The attack requires only that an attacker can view encrypted messages, can make the user make arbitrary encrypted requests, and that arbitrary plaintext can be added to ongoing requests. In the described attack, the user is made to request a package with a padded end such that the first byte of unknown information in the request is isolated in an encryption with only public information. The attacker then makes guesses at that byte of information, appending plaintext to the request and watching the encrypted channel for a message block that matches the block containing the unknown byte of information. At that point, the guess that resulted in that message block is identified as the correct guess. The process is then repeated with a smaller padding until the user’s package request header (including their HTTPS cookies) are known to the attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/paddingoracle/beast.png&#34; alt=&#34;beast&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure: &lt;/em&gt;Attacker (Mallory) is able to sniff encrypted traffic, force Alice to send cookie-bearing HTTP requests, and insert forged plaintexts in the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few issues mentioned associated with this attack, but that by using one of a variety of plugins, an attacker could make the user open bi-directional communication with the server. On this communication channel, the privileges required by the attacker to mount the attack would be easier to gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar in the vein of the BEAST attack using bitwise XOR operations to glean useful plaintext information, Lucky Thirteen offers yet another alternative means to get partial or even full plaintext recovery with just a simple man-in-the-middle injecting ciphertext into the original ciphertext. Based on analyzing how TLS and DTLS decrypt when given ciphertext, these attacks also rely on the CBC-mode from within these protocols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lucky-13-plaintext-recovery-from-injected-ciphertext&#34;&gt;Lucky 13: Plaintext Recovery from Injected Ciphertext&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;lucky-thirteen-breaking-the-tls-and-dtls-record-protocols-http-www-isg-rhul-ac-uk-tls-tlstiming-pdf-by-nadhem-j-alfardan-and-kenneth-g-paterson-2013&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isg.rhul.ac.uk/tls/TLStiming.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lucky Thirteen: Breaking the TLS and DTLS Record Protocols&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Nadhem J. Alfardan and Kenneth G. Paterson (2013)&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AlFardan and Paterson published a paper on the Lucky 13 attack in 2013.  The attack relies on a timing channel introduced by the difference in processing time between TLS records with good and bad padding, requiring only a standard man-in-the-middle attacker for execution and providing recovered plaintext in the most severe case.  This would indicate a major security flaw, even in comparison to the aforementioned BEAST attack; BEAST required capabilities beyond simple MITM on the part of the attacker.  As a result, the authors of the paper disclosed their results to all major vendors to allow for patching before publishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name “Lucky 13” is a reference to a specific breakpoint in the size of the padding on a given message.  Both TLS and DTLS use the HMAC algorithm to compute MAC tags for messages.  HMAC operates using a compression function on messages with lengths equal to multiples of 64 bytes, so TLS and DTLS pad out messages with remaining space.  After subtracting 8 bytes for the length field and 1 byte of mandatory padding, we are left with a maximum message length of 55 bytes that can be encoded within one block.  This means that messages less than 55 bytes can be processed with only four compression function evaluations, and that in general the number of compressions is equal to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$\left\lceil\frac{l-55}{64}\right\rceil+4$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;for messages of L bytes.  The compression function is relatively expensive, so the difference between 4 and 5 iterations is distinguishable in good conditions.  It is also possible to submit multiple requests as described below to amplify the differences if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors detail first a distinguishing attack, and then a variation allowing for full plaintext recovery.  All attacks rely on the timing channel.  Specifically, the authors describe in detail how it is possible to place a target ciphertext block at the end of an encrypted record, causing the decryption function to interpret the plaintext block corresponding to the ciphertext block as padding.  Thus the amount of time required to process that block depends on plaintext bytes, leaking information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/paddingoracle/timing.png&#34; alt=&#34;lucky-thirteen&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure:&lt;/em&gt; Graph showing the differences in timing due to the number of compressions necessary for varying lengths of bytes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isg.rhul.ac.uk/tls/TLStiming.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.isg.rhul.ac.uk/tls/TLStiming.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these readings and their respective explanations, we see that cryptographic protocols are often broken and need to be patched. There is always some threat model out there looking to exploit the first sign of weakness to decrypt and listen in on what should be a secure, encrypted channel. Through this last week, we focused on looking at padding oracle attacks which take advantage of the padding on the respective blocks in a CBC chain as they are passed from operation to operation. With the last word oracle and the BEAST attack, we saw how important this padding was to the security of the whole operation. With our look at Lucky 13, we were able to see that people were able to exploit the fact that one extra compression had to be done in certain situations to glean information about the message. As such, we see just from the padding, we have so many attacks. There are so many aspects to SSL/TLS protocols that so many more exploits exist. So, what are ways that we can prevent these attacks? With the padding attacks, we saw that they tried standardizing messages (but, why not just encrypt the message and send it back?). Should our strategy just be to move as quickly to the newest version of the security protocols? Should we add the MAC to the messages after encryption? On that note, it is important to bring to the attention of the readers, that TLS 1.3 (the most recent release) has been drafted (and in the process of release) and has resolved many of these issues that have exploited weaknesses present in older versions of the protocol. However, its adoption rate has been very low and so it is important to bring this up as more and more operations should be moved over to TLS 1.3, as this seems to be the most secure system we have available right now and thus should be adopted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/analysisssl3.pdf&#34;&gt;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/analysisssl3.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iacr.org/cryptodb/archive/2002/EUROCRYPT/2850/2850.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.iacr.org/cryptodb/archive/2002/EUROCRYPT/2850/2850.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/beast.pdf&#34;&gt;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/beast.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isg.rhul.ac.uk/tls/TLStiming.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.isg.rhul.ac.uk/tls/TLStiming.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The First Few Milliseconds of an TLS 1.2 Connection</title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/first-few-milliseconds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/first-few-milliseconds/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, Jeff Moser published &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.moserware.com/2009/06/first-few-milliseconds-of-https.html&#34;&gt;an excellent article&lt;/a&gt; on the first few milliseconds of an HTTP request. It described in detail how TLS 1.0 connections are established, including a great description of RSA. We&amp;rsquo;ve attempted to build and adapt upon that article here by describing how the process works for a TLS 1.2 connection. As of January 2nd 2017, TLS 1.2 has roughly &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trustworthyinternet.org/ssl-pulse/&#34;&gt;83.2% adoption&lt;/a&gt; among top websites, so now is a great time to dive in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of conecting via TLS 1.2 begins when the user attempts to navigate to a website. For this description, we are attempting to navigate to &lt;a href=&#34;https://example.com/&#34;&gt;https://example.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tls-layers&#34;&gt;TLS Layers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TLS protocol is composed of several layers, which come together to form each request. Here are descriptions of the common layers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/gnutls-layers.png&#34; alt=&#34;tls layers&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transport Layer&lt;/strong&gt; - The protocol over which TLS data is distributed. For HTTPS, this will be TCP. Needs only to be reliable (packet loss must be handled). Not a direct part of TLS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record Layer&lt;/strong&gt; - The record layer handles sending/receiving TLS messages, including data fragmentation for packets, (optional and bad) compression, and encryption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next three are common protocols that operate within the body of the Record Layer. TLS extensions can specify additional protocols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Handshake Protocol&lt;/strong&gt; - Responsible for choosing a cipher suite, connection parameters, and coordinating a shared secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alert Procotol&lt;/strong&gt; - Used to communicate warnings and errors. The most common alerts are for an invalid server certificate or to signal the end of a TLS connection when the client exits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application Protocol&lt;/strong&gt; - Raw higher-level application data transmitted by TLS. For us, this is HTTP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, onto the first few milliseconds of a TLSv1.2 request!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;part-0-the-record-layer&#34;&gt;Part 0: The Record Layer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the following packets will be wrapped in a Record Layer struct, it&amp;rsquo;s worth describing that here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/record-layer.png&#34; alt=&#34;record layer struct&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The record packet specifies the Content Type of the request, the TLS version, data length, and then the content data (in this image, a handshake clienthello).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the version specified in the record layer is often different from that specified in the handshake. This is for compatibility with some old TLS/SSL servers. You will often see the version here specified as TLS 1.0 (0x0103, or SSL 3.0)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;part-1-client-hello&#34;&gt;Part 1: Client Hello&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our web browser (Microsoft Edge 38.14393.0.0 on Windows 10) will begin the TLS 1.2 handshake with a ClientHello record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/client-hello.png&#34; alt=&#34;clienthello record&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see several important fields here worth mentioning. First, the &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt; (GMT seconds since midnight Jan 1, 1970) and &lt;strong&gt;random&lt;/strong&gt; bytes are included. This will be used later in the protocol to generate our symmetric encryption key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The client can send an optional &lt;strong&gt;session ID&lt;/strong&gt; (not sent in this case) to quickly resume a previous TLS connection and skip portions of the TLS handshake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably the most important part of the ClientHello message is the list of &lt;strong&gt;cipher suites&lt;/strong&gt;, which dictate the key exchange algorithm, bulk encryption algorithm (with key length), MAC, and a psuedo-random function. The list should be ordered by client preference. The collection of these choices is a &amp;ldquo;cipher suite&amp;rdquo;, and the server is responsible for choosing a secure one it supports, or return an error if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t support any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final field specified in the specification is for &lt;strong&gt;compression methods&lt;/strong&gt;. However, secure clients will advertise that they do not support compression (by passing &amp;ldquo;null&amp;rdquo; as the only algorithm) to avoid the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CRIME_(security_exploit)&#34;&gt;CRIME attack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the ClientHello can have a number of different extensions. A common one is &lt;strong&gt;server_name&lt;/strong&gt;, which specifies the hostname the connection is meant for, so webservers hosting multiple sites can present the correct certificate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;server-hello&#34;&gt;Server Hello&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the server has processed our ClientHello, it will respond with a TLSv1.2 ServerHello message&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/server-hello.png&#34; alt=&#34;serverhello message&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message returns several important fields, beginning with the TLS &lt;strong&gt;version&lt;/strong&gt; to be used, usually the highest version supported by both client and server. It also includes the server &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt; (not sure why example.com is so off!) and 28 &lt;strong&gt;random bytes&lt;/strong&gt; for use later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The server also makes a &lt;strong&gt;cipher suite selection&lt;/strong&gt; from the list chosen by the client. This should be the strongest suite supported by both. In our case, the server has chosen TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256, indicating the following:
* Key Exchange: Elliptic curve diffie-hellman, signed with RSA
* Encryption: AES in GCM mode with 128 bit keys
* MAC: SHA256&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;certificate&#34;&gt;Certificate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the ServerHello, the server will send a certificate chain to the client if applicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/server-certificate.png&#34; alt=&#34;server certificate message&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each certificate comes with information about domains it supports, who it was issued by, and the time period (start and end) of its validity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The certificate chain is a list of certificates beginning with the TLS certificate for the current domain, and ending in a root certificate that is built-in to the web browser. Each certificate is signed by the certificate above it in the chain, and it is this chain that the client validates to verify the server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case, example.com has a certificate issued by &amp;ldquo;DigiCert SHA2 High Assurance&amp;rdquo;, which in turn is issued by the root certificate &amp;ldquo;DigiCert High Assurance EV Root CA.&amp;rdquo; On Windows, you can view the list of root certificates on your system with &lt;code&gt;certmgr.msc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/certmgr.png&#34; alt=&#34;certmgr&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see the DigiCert High Assurance EV Root CA in our store, along with several other DigiCert certificates. OSX allows you to see root certificates using the &amp;ldquo;Keychain Access&amp;rdquo; program, where they are listed under &amp;ldquo;System Roots&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/keychain-access.png&#34; alt=&#34;osx keychain access&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, browsers will defer to the operating system root certificates as the central store for their validation. One notable exception is Firefox, which uses its own certificate store and ignores system root certificates by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Root CA certificates are implicitly trusted by every system they&amp;rsquo;re included on. An attacker who manages to control their private key could impersonate any website without raising any red flags, so it&amp;rsquo;s important that the certificate authorities keep them safe (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mail-archive.com/dev-security-policy@lists.mozilla.org/msg05455.html&#34;&gt;but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t always happen&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;optional-certificate-status-ocsp&#34;&gt;Optional: Certificate Status (OCSP)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One increasingly common extension is the Online Certificate Status Protocol (OCSP), used for certificate revocations. OCSP servers can be consulted by clients to check if the server certificate has been revoked, which helps solve a critical problem with TLS certificates. Servers response to certificate requests by issuing a signed response from the CA with a status code indicating whether or not the certificate is valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to wide deployment of OCSP, TLS vendors shipped certificate revocation lists (CRLs) that contained serial numbers of revoked certificates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce load, servers often cache the OCSP response and send it as a Certificate Status TLS message (OCSP stapling). This helps reduce load on the OCSP system and protects attackers from analyzing OCSP requests to determine client browsing habits. The server will send this cached message in response to a &lt;strong&gt;status_request&lt;/strong&gt; extension in the ClientHello message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/ocsp-stapling.png&#34; alt=&#34;ocsp stapling&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each OCSP ticket is signed by a trusted OCSP server. The response itself consists of a &lt;strong&gt;responseStatus&lt;/strong&gt; and optional &lt;strong&gt;responseBytes&lt;/strong&gt; with additional information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/ocsp-response.png&#34; alt=&#34;ocsp response info&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case, the OCSP ticket is valid and cached for 7 days (1/20 to 1/27). The server itself is responsible for refreshing its OCSP ticket at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;serverkeyexchange&#34;&gt;ServerKeyExchange&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For DHE key-exchanges (DHE_DSS, DHE_RSA, and DH_anon), the server will use a ServerKeyExchange message to specify the parameters for the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/dhe-params.png&#34; alt=&#34;dhe parameters&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The server has specified a &lt;strong&gt;named_curve&lt;/strong&gt; curve type using the &lt;strong&gt;secp256r1&lt;/strong&gt; elliptic curve (also known as &lt;strong&gt;P-256&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;prime256v1&lt;/strong&gt;). This is a public &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.secg.org/sec2-v2.pdf&#34;&gt;NIST standard curve&lt;/a&gt;. With knowledge of the curve to be used, both the server and client will know the crucial $p$ and $G$ values for ECDHE. For secp256r1, these are defined by NIST as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;p = FFFFFFFF 00000001 00000000 00000000 00000000 FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFF

G = 03 6B17D1F2 E12C4247 F8BCE6E5 63A440F2 77037D81 2DEB33A0 F4A13945 D898C296
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The server will choose a random private key and compute $a*G$ as its &lt;strong&gt;public key&lt;/strong&gt;. In addition to this it also signs the data with its private key - signing &lt;code&gt;SHA256(client_random + server_random + server_params)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;server-hello-done&#34;&gt;Server Hello Done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/server-hello-done.png&#34; alt=&#34;serverhellodone&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This short message from the server tells the client it&amp;rsquo;s done sending information. Nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clientkeyexchange&#34;&gt;ClientKeyExchange&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the client must  send its own ephemeral public key (for DH).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/client-dhe-key.png&#34; alt=&#34;client dhe key&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is calculated by generating a random private key $b$ and from there calculating $b*G$ as its public key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;completing-the-key-exchange&#34;&gt;Completing the Key Exchange&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the client has $a*G$ and the server $b*G$, both can calculate the final secret value $a*b*G$ with their own private keys. This is known as the &lt;strong&gt;pre-master secret&lt;/strong&gt;. The key detail here is that calculating $a*b*G$ from $a*G$ and $b*G$ alone is computationally difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just have one final step to convert our pre-master secret into the final &lt;strong&gt;master secret&lt;/strong&gt;. We will use the random bytes generated by the client and server earlier along with our chosen psuedo-random function. For us, that was SHA-256.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;master_secret = PRF(pre_master_secret, &amp;quot;master secret&amp;quot;, client_random + server_random)[0..47]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TLS 1.2 spec defines the PRF as &lt;code&gt;PRF(secret, label, seed)&lt;/code&gt; which expands to &lt;code&gt;P_SHA256(secret, label + seed)&lt;/code&gt;. The label is the literal ASCII string &amp;ldquo;master secret&amp;rdquo; without any null terminator. This expands to the following definition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;P_sha256(secret, seed) = HMAC_sha256(secret, A(1) + seed) +
                         HMAC_sha256(secret, A(2) + seed) +
                         HMAC_sha256(secret, A(3) + seed) +
                         ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;A(x)&lt;/code&gt; is defined recursively as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;A(0) = seed
A(x) = HMAC_sha256(secret, A(x-1))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of the PRF is the final key that will be used for the bulk of the crypto in our application. We only want 48 bytes here, so we would need 2 rounds of SHA-256 and would discard the extra data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;client-changecipherspec&#34;&gt;Client ChangeCipherSpec&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final unencrypted message sent by the client will be a ChangeCipherSpec message, which indicates that all following messages will be encrypted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/change-cipher-spec.png&#34; alt=&#34;changecipherspec message&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;client-finished-server-changecipherspec-and-server-finished&#34;&gt;Client Finished, Server ChangeCipherSpec, and Server Finished&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after sending a ChangeCipherSpec message, the client will send an encrypted Handshake Finished message to ensure the server is able to understand the agreed-upon encryption. The message will contain a &lt;strong&gt;hash of all previous handshake messages&lt;/strong&gt;, along with the string &amp;ldquo;client finished&amp;rdquo;. This is very important because it verifies that no part of the handshake has been tampered with by an attacker. It also includes the random bytes that were sent by the client and server, protecting it from replay attacks where the attacker pretends to be one of the parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once received by the server, the server will acknowledge with its own ChangeCipherSpec message, followed immediately by its own Finished message verifying the contents of the handshake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: if you have been following along in Wireshark, there appears to be a bug with Client/Server Finish messages when using AES_GCM that mislabels them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;application-data&#34;&gt;Application Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we can begin to transmit encrypted data! It may seem like a lot of work, but that is soon to pay off. The only remaining step is to discuss how the data is encrypted with AES_GCM, an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Authenticated_encryption&#34;&gt;AEAD&lt;/a&gt; cipher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we generate a MAC, key, and IV for both the client and the server using our master secret and the PRF definition from earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;key_data = PRF(master_secret, &amp;quot;key expansion&amp;quot;, server_random + client_random);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we are using 128-bit AES with SHA-256, we&amp;rsquo;ll pull out the following key data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// client_write_MAC_key = key_data[0..31]
// server_write_MAC_key = key_data[32..63]
client_write_key = key_data[64..79]
server_write_key = key_data[80..95]
client_write_IV = key_data[96..99]
server_write_IV = key_data[100..103]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For AEAD ciphers like GCM, we don&amp;rsquo;t need the MAC keys, but we offset them anyways. The client and server also get different keys to prevent a replay attack where a client message it looped back to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also construct &lt;code&gt;additional_data&lt;/code&gt; and an 8-byte &lt;code&gt;nonce&lt;/code&gt;, both of which are sent with the encrypted data. In the past, it was thought that the nonce could be either random or just a simple session counter. However, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nonce-disrespect/nonce-disrespect&#34;&gt;recent research&lt;/a&gt; found many sites using random nonces for AES_GCM were vulnerable to nonce reuse attacks, so it&amp;rsquo;s best to just use an incrementing counter tied to the session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;additional_data = sequence_num + record_type + tls_version + length
nonce = &amp;lt;random_8_bytes&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we can encrypt our data with AES GCM!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;encrypted = AES_GCM(client_write_key, client_write_IV+nonce, &amp;lt;DATA&amp;gt;, additional_data)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the server can read it with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;DATA&amp;gt; = AES_GCM(client_write_key, client_write_IV+nonce, encrypted, additional_data)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/images/firstfew/tls-hs-ecdhe.png&#34; alt=&#34;tls 1.2 ecdhe handshake&#34; /&gt;
(source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://timtaubert.de/blog/2015/11/more-privacy-less-latency-improved-handshakes-in-tls-13/&#34;&gt;More Privacy, Less Latency: Improved Handshakes in TLS version 1.3&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all it takes to make a TLS 1.2 connection! Over the course of ~103ms, we established a bidirectional encrypted tunnel and sent a full HTTP request and response in only 2 round trips. Although we didn&amp;rsquo;t cover nearly everything in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5246&#34;&gt;full TLS 1.2 RFC&lt;/a&gt;, we hope you have a pretty good overview of how process functions - and how much work goes in behind the scenes to secure web traffic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.moserware.com/2009/06/first-few-milliseconds-of-https.html&#34;&gt;http://www.moserware.com/2009/06/first-few-milliseconds-of-https.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://security.stackexchange.com/questions/131724/the-first-few-milliseconds-of-an-https-connection-tls-1-2-tls-echde-rsa-with&#34;&gt;https://security.stackexchange.com/questions/131724/the-first-few-milliseconds-of-an-https-connection-tls-1-2-tls-echde-rsa-with&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5246&#34;&gt;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5246&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5288&#34;&gt;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5288&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.secg.org/sec2-v2.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.secg.org/sec2-v2.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vincent.bernat.im/en/blog/2011-ssl-perfect-forward-secrecy.html&#34;&gt;https://vincent.bernat.im/en/blog/2011-ssl-perfect-forward-secrecy.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nonce-disrespect/nonce-disrespect&#34;&gt;https://github.com/nonce-disrespect/nonce-disrespect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trustworthyinternet.org/ssl-pulse/&#34;&gt;https://www.trustworthyinternet.org/ssl-pulse/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogging Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/blogging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/blogging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are some suggestions for how to create the class blog posts for
your assigned classes.  I believe each team has at least a few members
with enough experience using git and web contruction tools that
following these instructions won&amp;rsquo;t be a big burden, but if you have
other ways you want to build your blog page for a topic let me know
and we can discuss alternative options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;.  Hugo is a static website
generator that builds a site from Markdown pages.  (With homebrew on
Mac OS X, this is easy: &lt;code&gt;brew update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; brew install hugo&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clone the github repository,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tlseminar/tlseminar.github.io&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://github.com/tlseminar/tlseminar.github.io&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
This is what is used to build the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io&#34;&gt;tlseminar.github.io&lt;/a&gt; site.  If you are
working with multiple teammates on the blog post (which you probably
should be), you can add write permissions for everyone to the cloned
repository.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should create your page in the &lt;code&gt;web/content/post/&lt;/code&gt;
subdirectory. You can start by copying an earlier file in that
directory (e.g., &lt;code&gt;class1.md&lt;/code&gt;) and updating the header section
(between the &lt;code&gt;+++&lt;/code&gt; marks) and replacing everything after that with
your content.  Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to update the date so your page will
appear in the right order.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can use multiple files (but probably only one in
the &lt;code&gt;post/&lt;/code&gt; directory (this will show up as pages on the front
list).  Use the &lt;code&gt;web/content/images&lt;/code&gt; directory for images and the
&lt;code&gt;web/content/docs&lt;/code&gt; directory for papers.  Using images and other
resources to make your post interesting and visually compelling is
highly encouraged!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write the blog page using Markdown.  Markdown is a simple markup
language that can be used to easily generate both HTML and other
output document formats.  You can probably figure out everything you
need by looking at previous posts, but for a summary of Markdown,
see &lt;a href=&#34;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax&#34;&gt;Markdown: Syntax&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To test the post, run &lt;code&gt;make develop&lt;/code&gt; (in the &lt;code&gt;web/&lt;/code&gt; subdirectory of
your repository).  This starts the Hugo development server, usually
on port 1313 (unless that port is already in use).  Then, you can
view the site with a browser at &lt;code&gt;localhost:1313&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you are ready, submit a pull request to incorporate your
changes into the main repository (and public course website).  At
this stage, I will probably make things visible on the public site,
although it can still be edited and improved with subsequent
comments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class 1: Introduction</title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/class1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/class1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;c819c3c91461456ca328e97a753f6d56&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.77777777777778&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;plan&#34;&gt;Plan&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Find your team, introduce yourselves and figure out a management structure and plan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bid for your role:&lt;br /&gt;
T (lead Class 2: oracle padding attacks)&lt;br /&gt;
L (blog Class 1/lead 3: breaking weak asymmetric crypto, Drown)&lt;br /&gt;
S (lead Class 4: certificates)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;examining-certificates&#34;&gt;Examining Certificates&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When does the certificate for &lt;a href=&#34;https://whitehouse.gov&#34;&gt;https://whitehouse.gov&lt;/a&gt; expire?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;(won&amp;rsquo;t be able to answer this until later today) Does the new adminstration&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://whitehouse.gov&#34;&gt;https://whitehouse.gov&lt;/a&gt; site use the same private key as Obama&amp;rsquo;s?  (What should the answer to this question be?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;first-few-milliseconds&#34;&gt;First Few Milliseconds&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff Moser&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.moserware.com/2009/06/first-few-milliseconds-of-https.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The First Few Milliseconds of an HTTPS Connection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wireshark.org/download.html&#34;&gt;Wireshark&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start Wireshark, and look at all the TLS sessions running on your
laptop.  How many different TLS sessions are there?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pick one of the TLS sessions and try to figure out what application
is using it.  Who are the endpoints?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assuming (for now!) the encryption is all perfect, what could
someone intercepting the traffic learn?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What differences can you observe compared to what is described for the TLS 1.0 connections on that web page?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Background Preparation</title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/background/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/background/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Here are some suggestions for getting the necessary background for the
seminar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cryptography&#34;&gt;Cryptography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have already taken a cryptography course, you should have
enough cryptography background already.  If not, here are some
suggested ways to get enough crypo background over winter break to be
ready for the seminar.  I believe that for most students, the best way
to get the expected background for this course is to take my Applied
Cryptography course (more info below), but there are many options, and
lots of great resources that go into much more depth than my course if
you have more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-line-courses&#34;&gt;On-Line Courses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/course/applied-cryptography--cs387&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Udacity cs387: Applied
Cryptography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
- this is an open on-line course that you can take anytime taught by
myself (so I am somewhat partial to it!).  There are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~evans/courses/cs387/&#34;&gt;some additional
materials for the course
available&lt;/a&gt;,
including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~evans/courses/crypto-notes.pdf&#34;&gt;extensive course notes
(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;
created by Daniel Winter.  This is a very short and informal
introduction to cryptography, which would be enough background to be
prepared for the seminar.  (I can&amp;rsquo;t give an unbiased assessment of the
course, but according to Information Week, it is a recommended course
to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.informationweek.com/strategic-cio/team-building-and-staffing/5-online-classes-to-pump-up-it-careers/d/d-id/898915&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pump Up IT
Careers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href=&#34;www.prospectmagazine.co.uk/magazine/online-universities-udacity-grand-challenge-david-stavens-dave-evans&#34;&gt;Prospect
Magazine&lt;/a&gt;
claimed the instructor has a &amp;ldquo;Monty Python humor&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;cult
following&amp;rdquo;, although you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t believe everything you read in
British magazines.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Boneh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/crypto&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cryptography
Course&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (offered through
Coursera).  The materials from previous courses are not available
(although you may be able to find them if you are resourceful), so you
have to take the course when it is offered by Coursera. There is a
session starting December 26.  This is an excellent course that is a
bit longer and goes into more depth on many topics than my course.
You can read &lt;a href=&#34;http://bryanpendleton.blogspot.com/2012/05/comparing-coursera-and-udacity.html&#34;&gt;Bryan Pendleton&amp;rsquo;s more objective
comparison&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christoff Parr and Jan Pelzl&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crypto-textbook.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding
Cryptography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; textbook includes
Parr&amp;rsquo;s excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.crypto.rub.de/Buch/movies.php&#34;&gt;video
lectures&lt;/a&gt; (chalkboard
style without editing, so takes some patience to watch).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;textbooks&#34;&gt;Textbooks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crypto101.io/&#34;&gt;Crypto 101&lt;/a&gt; - a very easy to read and
practically-focused introduction to cryptography (available as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/Crypto101.pdf&#34;&gt;free,
creative-commons licensed PDF&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.umd.edu/~jkatz/imc.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to Modern
Cryptography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Jonathan Katz
and Yehuda Lindell.  This provides a lot more depth that is required
for joining the seminar, but is an excellent book for ambitious
students with more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;computing-systems&#34;&gt;Computing Systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students in the class will benefit from understanding computing
systems and having experience with systems-level programming at least
at the level of a typical introductory operating systems course.
Students without this experience will either need to put a lot of
effort into learning it, or select projects and presentation topics
that focus on other aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some resources for learning about computing systems are below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ops-class.org/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hack the Kernel&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; - Operating Systems
class developed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bluegroup.systems/people/gwa/&#34;&gt;Geoffrey
Challen&lt;/a&gt;.  Provides
programming assignments you can try on your own, as well as video
lectures and lots of on-line materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rust-class.org/&#34;&gt;cs4414: Operating Systems&lt;/a&gt; - Operating
systems course I taught in Fall 2013 and Spring 2014. Includes
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rust-class.org/pages/classes.html&#34;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; of lectures, and
programming assignments in Rust (some of which will need some updating
to work in the latest version of Rust).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMU&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://csapp.cs.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;Computing Systems&lt;/a&gt; course and
textbook by Randal Bryant and David O&amp;rsquo;Hallaron provides an excellent
introduction to systems programming, as well as a series of &lt;a href=&#34;http://csapp.cs.cmu.edu/3e/labs.html&#34;&gt;fun
self-study labs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rust-programming&#34;&gt;Rust Programming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m hoping several of the projects will involve contribution to open
source projects using Rust to provide secure, efficient, and
iter-operable implementations of TLS and other cryptographic
functionalities.  It is not a requirement that you use Rust in this
class, but everyone will be encouraged to get some experience with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doc.rust-lang.org/nightly/book/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rust Programming Language
Book&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (this is the
&amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; Rust book, which includes a tutorial to get started)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aml3.github.io/RustTutorial/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rust Tutorial&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (this was
developed for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://rust-class.org/&#34;&gt;cs4414 class&lt;/a&gt; by Alex
Lamana, Rob Michaels, and Wil Thomason.  (Some parts may need updating
to latest version of Rust, so if you go through this, please submit
updates as pull requests!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rustbyexample.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rust by Example&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to TLSeminar!</title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/1353/&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;//imgs.xkcd.com/comics/heartbleed.png&#34; title=&#34;I looked at some of the data dumps from vulnerable sites, and it was ... bad. I saw emails, passwords, password hints. SSL keys and session cookies. Important servers brimming with visitor IPs. Attack ships on fire off the shoulder of Orion, c-beams glittering in the dark near the Tannhäuser Gate. I should probably patch OpenSSL.&#34; alt=&#34;Heartbleed&#34; srcset=&#34;//imgs.xkcd.com/comics/heartbleed_2x.png 2x&#34;&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the course site for &lt;strong&gt;cs6501: Understanding and Securing
TLS&lt;/strong&gt;. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/syllabus&#34;&gt;Syllabus&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first class is Friday, 20 January 2017 (9:30am-noon in Thornton
Hall D115).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/projectideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/projectideas/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-ideas&#34;&gt;Project Ideas&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This page collects some ideas for projects.  It is meant as a starting
point to help you think of things that might be interesting to do, not
to limit your possibilities.  Any topic that is related to TLS and the
ecosystem around TLS is within scope for your project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deployment-in-practice&#34;&gt;Deployment in Practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why do the servers running critical sensitive services for UVA
appear to be so insecure?  What are the impediments in practice to
making services like
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ssllabs.com/ssltest/analyze.html?d=collab.virginia.edu&amp;amp;latest&#34;&gt;collab&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ssllabs.com/ssltest/analyze.html?d=sis.virginia.edu&amp;amp;latest&#34;&gt;sis&lt;/a&gt;
more secure?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;proxy-protected-server&#34;&gt;Proxy-Protected Server&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can&amp;rsquo;t we provide a simple proxy service in front of a web
server that implements a simple, secure TLS endpoint?  What are the
latency and overhead costs of implementing a server this way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;configuration&#34;&gt;Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make it possible to configure a web server to use different
certificates with different key pairs for different protocols and
connection types.  (Motivated most immediately by the DROWN attack.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contribute to tools automating use of ACME (e.g., for Let&amp;rsquo;s Encrypt
certificates).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;client-ui&#34;&gt;Client UI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of the security indicators used by a browser can be spoofed,
and few users understand what parts of the current UI can be
&amp;ldquo;trusted&amp;rdquo; (controlled by the web browser core) and what parts are
untrusted (controlled by the web page).  Reconsider the web client
UI in a way that provides a stronger and clearer boundary between
trustworthy and site-controlled content.  [&lt;a href=&#34;https://textslashplain.com/2017/01/14/the-line-of-death/&#34;&gt;The Line of
Death&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why not put the favicon for a site in its SSL certificate?  How hard
would it be to extend the current infrastructure to support this,
and to provide a browser client that displays trusted favicon
images.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;protecting-resources&#34;&gt;Protecting Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://heartbleed.com/&#34;&gt;Heartbleed&lt;/a&gt; shocked the Internet for a while mainly because it allowed for remote attackers to access data in the server&amp;rsquo;s memory, most importantly the server&amp;rsquo;s private key. Heartbleed was a realization of an important concept: attacking a service and stealing data from the server&amp;rsquo;s memory. There are numerous practical examples of web-based services that can become vulnerable to this type of attack. Can we mitigate this risk by using tools at the programming language level? A combination of Rust&amp;rsquo;s language guarantees and a memory protection system might be the answer! Checkout &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ctz/rustls&#34;&gt;Rustls&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/halmohri/fc&#34;&gt;fidelius charm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Memory corruption vulnerabilities in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnutls.org/security.html&#34;&gt;GnuTLS&lt;/a&gt; form another opportunity to apply fidelius charm, a memory protection library for Rust, to secure interactions with clients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decentralization&#34;&gt;Decentralization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Design and prototype a &lt;em&gt;decentralized certificate authority&lt;/em&gt;, where
no single entity controls the signing keys, but a multi-party
protocol is used to produce a new certificate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is there a way to do CloudFlare-style, we make your site appear to
support TLS, that is substantially better than what they do?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/readings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/readings/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;readings&#34;&gt;Readings&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transport_Layer_Security&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transport Layer
Security&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
page includes a quite extensive summary of TLS vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.moserware.com/2009/06/first-few-milliseconds-of-https.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The First Few Milliseconds of an HTTPS Connection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Jeff Moser, 2009.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://security.stackexchange.com/questions/131724/the-first-few-milliseconds-of-an-https-connection-tls-1-2-tls-echde-rsa-with&#34;&gt;Discussion about TLS1.2/1.3 Updates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;protocol-specification&#34;&gt;Protocol Specification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlswg.github.io/tls13-spec/&#34;&gt;The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version
1.3&lt;/a&gt; (Internet Draft, 22 December
2016 is latest version as of today, 29 December 2016.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier versions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5246&#34;&gt;The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/pdf/rfc5246.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;], August 2008.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3268&#34;&gt;Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) Ciphersuites for Transport Layer Security (TLS)&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/pdf/rfc3268.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;], June 2002.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6101&#34;&gt;The Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) Protocol Version 3.0&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/pdf/rfc6101.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;], August 2011.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc2246/&#34;&gt;The TLS Protocol Version 1.0&lt;/a&gt;, January 1999.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;protocol-analysis&#34;&gt;Protocol Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Wagner, Bruce Schneier. &lt;em&gt;Analysis of the SSL 3.0 Protocol&lt;/em&gt;.  In
&lt;em&gt;Second USENIX Workshop on Electronic Commerce Proceedings&lt;/em&gt;,
1996. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/analysisssl3.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attacks&#34;&gt;Attacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RFC on known attacks: &lt;em&gt;Summarizing Known Attacks on Transport Layer Security (TLS) and Datagram TLS (DTLS)&lt;/em&gt;. Y. Sheffer, et al. RFC 7457. February 2015. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7457&#34;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/pdf/rfc7457.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Bleichenbacher. &lt;em&gt;Chosen Ciphertext Attacks Against Protocols Based on the RSA Encryption Standard PKCS #1&lt;/em&gt;. CRYPTO 1998. [&lt;a href=&#34;http://archiv.infsec.ethz.ch/education/fs08/secsem/Bleichenbacher98.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serge Vaudenay. &lt;em&gt;Security Flaws Induced by CBC Padding Applications to
SSL, IPSEC, WTLS&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;. EuroCRYPT
2002. [&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iacr.org/cryptodb/archive/2002/EUROCRYPT/2850/2850.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Brumley and Daniel Boneh. &lt;em&gt;Remote Timing Attacks are Practical&lt;/em&gt;.  USENIX Security Symposium 2003, and Computer Networks, August 2005. &lt;a href=&#34;Followed by: Billy Bob Brumley and Nicola Tuveri. _Remote Timing Attacks are Still Practical_. ESORICS 2011 [[PDF](https://eprint.iacr.org/2011/232.pdf)] [[ePrint](https://eprint.iacr.org/2011/232)]&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/remotetiming.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brice Canvel, Alain Hiltgen, Serge Vaudenay, and Martin Vuagnoux. &lt;em&gt;Password Interception in a SSL/TLS Channel&lt;/em&gt;. CRYPTO 2003. [&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iacr.org/cryptodb/archive/2003/CRYPTO/1069/1069.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thai Duong and Juliano Rizzo. &lt;em&gt;Here Come The &amp;oplus; Ninjas&lt;/em&gt;.  2011. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/beast.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadhem AlFardan, Daniel J. Bernstein, Kenneth G. Paterson, Bertram Poettering, and Jacob C.N. Schuldt.
&lt;em&gt;On the Security of RC4 in TLS&lt;/em&gt;. USENIX Security Symposium 2013. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/usenixsecurity13/sec13-paper_alfardan.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usenix.org/conference/usenixsecurity13/technical-sessions/paper/alFardan&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadhem J. AlFardan and Kenneth G. Paterson. &lt;em&gt;Lucky Thirteen: Breaking the TLS and DTLS Record Protocols&lt;/em&gt;. IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (Oakland) 2013. [&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isg.rhul.ac.uk/tls/TLStiming.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isg.rhul.ac.uk/tls/Lucky13.html&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Adrian, Karthikeyan Bhargavan, Zakir Durumeric, Pierrick Gaudry,
Matthew Green, J. Alex Halderman, Nadia Heninger, Drew Springall,
Emmanuel Thomé, Luke Valenta, Benjamin VanderSloot, Eric Wustrow,
Santiago Zanella-Béguelin, and Paul Zimmermann. &lt;em&gt;Imperfect Forward
Secrecy: How Diffie-Hellman Fails in Practice&lt;/em&gt;.  22nd ACM Conference
on Computer and Communications Security (CCS ’15), October
2015. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/logjam.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://weakdh.org/&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nimrod Aviram, Sebastian Schinzel, Juraj Somorovsky, Nadia Heninger,
Maik Dankel, Jens Steube, Luke Valenta, David Adrian, J. Alex
Halderman, Viktor Dukhovni, Emilia Käsper, Shaanan Cohney, Susanne
Engels, Christof Paar, and Yuval Shavitt. &lt;em&gt;DROWN: Breaking TLS using
SSLv2&lt;/em&gt;. 25th USENIX Security Symposium, Austin, TX, August
2016. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/drown.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://drownattack.com/&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;formal-methods&#34;&gt;Formal Methods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John C. Mitchell, Vitaly Shmatikov, and Ulrich Stern. &lt;em&gt;Finite-State Analysis of SSL 3.0&lt;/em&gt;. USENIX Security Symposium, January 1998. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/finitestate.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lawrence C. Paulson. &lt;em&gt;Inductive Analysis of the Internet Protocol TLS&lt;/em&gt;. ACM Transactions of Information and System Security, August 1999. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/inductiveanalysis.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karthikeyan Bhargavan, Ricardo Corin, Cédric Fournet, Eugen Zalinescu.
&lt;em&gt;Cryptographically Verified Implementations for TLS&lt;/em&gt;. ACM CCS
2008. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/verifiedtls.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tibor Jager, Florian Kohlar, Sven Schäge, and Jörg Schwenk. &lt;em&gt;On the Security of TLS-DHE in the Standard Model&lt;/em&gt;. May 2011. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://eprint.iacr.org/2011/219&#34;&gt;eprint&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://eprint.iacr.org/2011/219.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Krawczyk, Hugo, Kenneth G. Paterson, and Hoeteck Wee. &lt;em&gt;On the Security of the TLS Protocol: A Systematic Analysis&lt;/em&gt;. CRYPTO 2013.
[&lt;a href=&#34;http://eprint.iacr.org/2013/339&#34;&gt;eprint&lt;/a&gt;]
[&lt;a href=&#34;http://eprint.iacr.org/2013/339.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karthikeyan Bhargavan, Cédric Fournet, Markulf Kohlweiss, Alfredo Pironti, Pierre-Yves Strub. &lt;em&gt;Implementing TLS with Verified Cryptographic Security&lt;/em&gt;
IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (Oakland), 2013. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/mitls.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/mitlstr.pdf&#34;&gt;Extended Tech Report, PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karthikeyan Bhargavan1, Cedric Fournet, Markulf Kohlweiss, Alfredo Pironti, Pierre-Yves Strub, and Santiago Zanella-Beguelin. &lt;em&gt;Proving the TLS Handshake Secure (As It Is)&lt;/em&gt;. CRYPTO 2014. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/provinghandshake.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;implementation-bugs&#34;&gt;Implementation Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martin Georgiev, Subodh Iyengar, Suman Jana, Rishita Anubhai, Dan
Boneh, Vitaly Shmatikov. &lt;em&gt;The Most Dangerous Code in the World:
Validating SSL Certificates in Non-Browser Software&lt;/em&gt;.  ACM CCS 2012.
[&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/mostdangerouscode.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Kaloper-Mersinjak, Hannes Mehnert, Anil Madhavapeddy and Peter Sewell. &lt;em&gt;Not-quite-so-broken TLS: lessons in re-engineering a security protocol
specification and implementation&lt;/em&gt;. USENIX Security 2015. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/nqsbtls.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Beurdouche, Karthikeyan Bhargavan, Antoine Delignat-Lavaud,
Cedric Fournet, Markulf Kohlweiss, Alfredo Pironti, Pierre-Yves Strub,
Jean Karim Zinzindohoue. &lt;em&gt;A Messy State of the Union: Taming the
Composite State Machines of TLS&lt;/em&gt;.  IEEE Symposium on Security and
Privacy (Oakland) 2015. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/mitlsunion.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rELp9-oFAw0&#34;&gt;Talk Video&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suman Jana, Yuan Kang, Samuel Roth, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://rayb.info/&#34;&gt;Baishakhi Ray&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Automatically Detecting Error Handling Bugs using Error Specifications&lt;/em&gt;. USENIX Security 2016. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/epex.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;testing&#34;&gt;Testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chad Brubaker, Suman Jana, &lt;a href=&#34;http://rayb.info/&#34;&gt;Baishakhi Ray&lt;/a&gt;, Sarfraz Khurshid, Vitaly Shmatikov.
&lt;em&gt;Using Frankencerts for Automated Adversarial Testing of Certificate Validation in SSL/TLS Implementations&lt;/em&gt;. IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (Oakland) 2014. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/frankencerts.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Beurdouche, Antoine Delignat-Lavaud, Nadim Kobeissi, Alfredo Pironti, Karthikeyan Bhargavan. &lt;em&gt;FLEXTLS: A Tool for Testing TLS Implementations&lt;/em&gt;.
USENIX Workshop on Offensive Technologies, 2015. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/flextls.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-and-cost&#34;&gt;Performance and Cost&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cristian Coarfa, Peter Druschel, and Dan S. Wallach. &lt;em&gt;Performance Analysis of TLS Web Servers&lt;/em&gt;.  ACM Transactions on Computer Systems (earlier version in NDSS 2002), February 2006. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/performance.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;certificates&#34;&gt;Certificates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Clark and Paul C. van Oorschot. &lt;em&gt;SoK: SSL and HTTPS: Revisiting
past challenges and evaluating certificate trust model
enhancements&lt;/em&gt;. IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (Oakland) 2013.
[&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/soktls.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Wendlandt, David G. Andersen, and Adrian Perrig. &lt;em&gt;Perspectives: Improving SSH-style Host Authentication with
Multi-Path Probing&lt;/em&gt;. USENIX ATC 2008. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/perspectives.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://perspectives-project.org/&#34;&gt;Project Site&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.certificate-transparency.org/&#34;&gt;Certificate Transparency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://letsencrypt.org/&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s Encrypt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-acme-acme/?include_text=1&#34;&gt;ACMS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;extensions&#34;&gt;Extensions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Naylor, Kyle Schomp, Matteo Varvello, Ilias Leontiadis, Jeremy Blackburn, Diego Lopez, Konstantina Papagiannaki, Pablo Rodriguez Rodriguez, and Peter Steenkiste. &lt;em&gt;Multi-Context TLS (mcTLS): Enabling Secure In-Network Functionality in TLS&lt;/em&gt;. SIGCOMM 2015. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/mcTLS.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-quantum&#34;&gt;Post-Quantum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joppe W. Bos, Craig Costello, Michael Naehrig, and Douglas
Stebila. &lt;em&gt;Post-quantum key exchange for the TLS protocol from the ring
learning with errors problem&lt;/em&gt;.  IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (Oakland) 2016.
[&lt;a href=&#34;http://eprint.iacr.org/2014/599.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BCmSzzQ2ges&#34;&gt;Talk Video&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erdem Alkim, Léo Ducas, Thomas Pöppelmann, and Peter Schwabe.
&lt;em&gt;Post-quantum Key Exchange—A New Hope&lt;/em&gt;.  USENIX Security Symposiumn 2016. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/usenixsecurity16/sec16_paper_alkim.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usenix.org/conference/usenixsecurity16/technical-sessions/presentation/alkim&#34;&gt;Talk Video&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/resources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Links to resources will be added here soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/schedule/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/schedule/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/teams&#34;&gt;Teams&lt;/a&gt; for the class teams and responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/class 1&#34;&gt;Class 1&lt;/a&gt; - Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/first-few-milliseconds&#34;&gt;The First Few Milliseconds of an TLS 1.2 Connection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class 2: Oracle Padding Attacks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/analysisssl3.pdf&#34;&gt;Analysis of the SSL 3.0
Protocol&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Important sections to read: 3.3, 5 (For a broad analysis of SSL vulnerabilities,
consider reading sections 3 and 4. Short-block padding attacks are
briefly mentioned in section 3.3.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iacr.org/cryptodb/archive/2002/EUROCRYPT/2850/2850.pdf&#34;&gt;Security Flaws Introduced by CBC Padding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Important Sections to read: 1, 3, 5.1, 7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/beast.pdf&#34;&gt;Here Come The XOR Ninjas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Important Sections to read: 1, 4.1, 4.2, 5.1, 5.2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isg.rhul.ac.uk/tls/TLStiming.pdf&#34;&gt;Lucky Thirteen: Breaking the TLS and DTLS Record Protocols&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Important Sections to read: 3, 4, 5, 7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class 3: Downgrade Attacks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class 4: Certificates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;syllabus&#34;&gt;Syllabus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;notpdf&#34;&gt;
   &lt;div class=&#34;printing&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/docs/syllabus.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF for Printing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!--endpdf--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cs6501-understanding-and-securing-tls&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cs6501: Understanding and Securing TLS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;University of Virginia, Spring 2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meetings:&lt;/strong&gt; Fridays, 9:30AM - noon, Thornton Hall D115&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Objective.&lt;/strong&gt; SSL/TLS is the world’s most important
  cryptographic protocol, used for every secure web connection and
  many other purposes. Every month it seems we hear about another new
  major vulnerability in TLS. In this project-focused seminar, we’ll
  take a deep dive into understanding how TLS came to be the mess it
  is today, look into some of the vulnerabilities in detail, and study
  methods for making TLS more secure. We will work as a group to
  contribute to open source projects to improve the security of TLS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expected Background:&lt;/strong&gt; Students are expected to enter the class with
  introductory background in cryptography (sufficient to understand
  symmetric and asymmetric cryptosystems, cryptographic hash
  functions, and digital signatures) and experience in systems
  programming (comparable to a good undergraduate operating systems
  course).  If you do not have this background, you are still welcome
  to take the course, but will need to do some work on your own to be
  prepared before the semester begins (see the course site for links
  to recommended preparation materials).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coordinators:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://halmohri.com/&#34;&gt;Hussain Almohri&lt;/a&gt; (visiting from Kuwait University)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/evans&#34;&gt;David Evans&lt;/a&gt; (evans@virginia.edu). My &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/evans/office&#34;&gt;office&lt;/a&gt; is Rice 507.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course-expectations&#34;&gt;Course Expectations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students in the seminar are expected to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lead discussions on interesting topics during the class meetings.
For each week, there will be two groups of two students charged with
preparing a topic and leading the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Particpate actively in class meetings.  This means being prepared to
contribute by doing the assigned preparation (which will typically
involve reading a few research papers, but may involve other things
also) and thinking about the materials deeply to be able to
contribute well to discussions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Produce scribe &amp;ldquo;blogs&amp;rdquo; for 2-3 topics.  For each topic, there will
be students assigned to write-up a blog about the topic to post on
the course site.  Students responsible for posting the blog summary
will be different from the ones charged with leading the topic
discussion, but should work closely with the leaders on the posted
write-up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work in a small team to conduct projects that will contribute
usefully to the TLS ecosystem. Projects may contribute to open
source implementations of TLS, provide resources for testing and
deploying TLS, analyze the state of TLS deployments today, or adress
other issues related to secure web connections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Work with the class to produce a systematization of knowledge paper
on the security of TLS.  Everyone will be expected to contribute to
this, with the goal of jointly producing a publishable paper that
systematizes what is currently known about TLS and the ecosystem
around it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;communications&#34;&gt;Communications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Website:&lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://tlseminar.github.io/&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  All
  course materials will be posted on the course website, and students
  will be expected to provide materials to add to this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slack:&lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.slack.com&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://tlseminar.slack.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  We
  will use a slack group for class communications.  You can join using
  any &lt;code&gt;@virginia.edu&lt;/code&gt; email address.  You can also create slack
  channels for your team communications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;honor-and-responsibility&#34;&gt;Honor and Responsibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe strongly in the value of a &lt;em&gt;community of trust&lt;/em&gt;, and expect
all of the students in this class to contribute to strenghtening and
enhancing that community.  The course will be better for everyone if
everyone can assume everyone else is trustworthy. The course staff
starts with the assumption that all students at the university deserve
to be trusted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this course, we will be learning about and exploring some
vulnerabilities that could be used to compromise &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ssllabs.com/ssltest/analyze.html?d=collab.virginia.edu&amp;amp;latest&#34;&gt;vunlerable
websites&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;You are trusted to behave responsibility and ethically.&lt;/strong&gt; You may
not attack any website without permission of the site owners, and may
not use anything you learn in this class for evil.  If you have any
doubts about whether or not something you want to do is ethical and
legal, you should check with the course instructor before proceeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;area-requirements&#34;&gt;Area Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note for CS Graduate Students.&lt;/strong&gt; This course is mislisted in SIS
(indeed, it is a &amp;ldquo;bug&amp;rdquo; in the setup of SIS that cannot be overcome
that requires all grad courses to be assigned areas) as counting for
the &amp;ldquo;Computer Systems&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Theory&amp;rdquo; area requirements.  As per the
actual rules, as a cs6501 seminar the course does not a priori count
for any particular areas.  It may be possible to count it for any
area, but it would be up to you to make the case to your committee
that it should count for a given area. In most cases, this will depend
a lot on what you individually do in the class - for example, you
could select presentation topics and a topic for you project that
would make a strong case for counting it for the &amp;ldquo;Theory&amp;rdquo; area, but
someone else who does a systems-focused project would be able to count
it for a different area. I can help provide guidance on this, but it
is ultimately up to your committee to decide if a course counts for a
particular area requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/teams/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;teams&#34;&gt;Teams&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: team names are temporary, and will map to teams on schedule.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr bgcolor=&#34;#CCC&#34;&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team Sesame&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team Cinnamon&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team Poppyseed&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Adam Imeson (aei5uj)&lt;Br&gt;
Benyi Gong (bg3va)&lt;br&gt;
Bethlehem Naylor (bn9eb)&lt;br&gt;
Bhuvanesh Murali (bm4cr)&lt;br&gt;
Haina Li (hl3wb)&lt;br&gt;
Joshua Holtzman (jmh2ba)&lt;br&gt;
Reid Bixler (rmb3yz)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Anant Kharkar (agk7uc)&lt;br&gt;
Bargav Jayaraman (bj4nq)&lt;br&gt;
Benjamin Lowman (brl2xx)&lt;br&gt;
Bill Young (wty5dn)&lt;br&gt;
Darion Cassel (dfc9ed)&lt;br&gt;
Sam Havron (sgh7cc)&lt;br&gt;
Vikram Patwardhan (vvp2da)&lt;br&gt;
Yuchi Tian (yt8mn)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Collin Berman (cmb5nh)&lt;br&gt;
Cyrus Malekpour (cm7bv)&lt;br&gt;
Haoran Liu (hl4fb)&lt;br&gt;
Daniel Saha (drs5ma)&lt;br&gt;
Minghua Jiang (mj2eu)&lt;br&gt;
Tianyi Jin (tj2cw)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;responsibilities&#34;&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each week (except for project proposal and presentation weeks),
one team will be responsible for Leading the class, one team for
writing a Blog post on the class topic, and one team for arranging
food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leading Team.&lt;/strong&gt;  The team responsible for leading a class should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two weeks before the scheduled class, meet briefly with the coordinator(s) to discuss plan for the class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One week before the scheduled class, go over detailed plan for class with coordinator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No later than one week before class: send out to the class Slack group the preparation materials for the class.  This can include links to papers to read, but could also include exercises to do or software to install and experiment with, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day of class: lead an interesting, engaging, and illuminating class!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After class: help the Blogging team by providing them with your materials, answering their questions, and reviewing their write-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blogging Team.&lt;/strong&gt; The team responsible for blogging a class should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The week before the scheduled class, do the preparation work posted by the lead team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The week before the scheduled class, develop a team plan for how to manage the blogging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During class, participate actively in the class, and take detailed notes (this can be distributed among the team).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the Tuesday following class, have a draft of the blog post ready, and share it with the rest of the class (including the leading team and coordinators) for comments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the next Friday (one week after the class), have a final version of the blog post ready to add to the course site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food Team.&lt;/strong&gt; The team responsible for food should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The week before the scheduled class, do the preparation work posted by the lead team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan among yourselves what food to bring and who is responsible.  If
you want to use my credit card to buy food, borrow it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring something yummy, but not too messy or disruptive, to class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the receipts to get reimbursed, and take care of the
reimbursement. (This is easiest if the reimbursee is someone already
set up in the CS department&amp;rsquo;s financial system.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr bgcolor=&#34;#CCC&#34;&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Date&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Topic&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td width=12%&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team T (Cinnamon)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td width=12%&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team L (Poppyseed)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td width=12%&gt;&lt;b&gt;Team S (Sesame)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 1 (20 Jan)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Intro&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Plan&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Plan&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 2 (27 Jan)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Padding Oracle Attacks&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 3 (3 Feb)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Logjam/DROWN&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 4 (10 Feb)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Certificates&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 5 (17 Feb)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TBD&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 6 (24 Feb)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TBD&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 7 (3 Mar)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TBD/Projects&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#66EEAA&#34; style=&#34;text-align:center&#34; colspan=5&gt;Spring Break&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 8 (17 Mar)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TBD&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 9 (24 Mar)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TBD&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 10 (31 Mar)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TBD&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 11 (7 Apr)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TBD&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 12 (14 Apr)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TBD&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 13 (31 Mar)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;TBD&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Food&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#44AAEE&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&#34;#CCDD55&#34;&gt;Lead&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class 14 (28 Apr)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mini-Conference&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>cs2102: Discrete Math</title>
      <link>https://tlseminar.github.io/main/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tlseminar.github.io/main/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the front page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tlseminar.github.io/syllabus&#34;&gt;Syllabus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>